Ramakrishna Makani

Software Research and Development Engineer

★ Kempten, Germany

ramakrishna.mak@gmail.com

+49 1788268028

Profile

Software Research and Development Engineer with a Master of Science degree in Automation and Robotics from TU Dortmund, Germany, with 3+ years of experience in Research and Development in the landscape of Industrial Automation with projects ranging from Embedded Systems, Communications, Sensors and Actuators, Control Systems. Self-driven and motivated to manage and handle projects independently and experience of planning and working with a team.

Areas of Expertise

Embedded Systems - Linux - Industry 4.0 - Open Platform Communications Unified Architecture (OPCUA) - Robotics - Microprocessors and Microcontrollers - Sensors - Software Design - Social Media and Technology Marketing

Education

M.Sc. Automation and Robotics, *Technische Universität Dortmund* Dortmund, Germany *Nov 2020 - Mar 2024* German Grade: 2,2 / 4

Relevant Courses: Embedded Systems, Robotics, Industrial Communication, Process Automation, Software Engineering B.E. Electronics and Instrumentation, RV College of Engineering Bengaluru, India Aug 2016 - Oct 2020

German converted Grade: 2,2 / 4

Relevant Courses: Embedded Systems, Control Systems, Microcontrollers and Microprocessors, Communication Networks, Programming in C/C++

Professional Experience

Embedded Software Developer, (BE.services GmbH)

Kempten (Allgäu), Germany 05/2024 - present

- Designed and Developed Pub/Sub over UDP transport layer in C++ for Matrikon's eFlex OPC UA SDK using with a low memory footprint for embedded devices.
- Developed the SDK for embedded devices with ultra low memory footprint (below 2KB RAM).
- Developed and released the first version of eTSN product, which is an engineered solution with OPC UA Pub/Sub and Time Sensitive Networking (TSN) for reliable, low latency real-time communication.
- Development planning, estimation and management of Git of the projects under the product.
- Drafted proposals alongwith universties and potential customers as part of pre-sales activities.
- Represented the company at trade fairs such as HannoverMesse, SPS and many Workshops.

Working Student, (SALZ Automation GmbH)

Bad Salzuflen, Germany 09/2022 - 03/2024

- Designed and Developed a Prototype for Controller-to-Controller communication to show Proof of Concept (PoC) towards OPC UA FX (Field eXchange).
- Implemented and maintained Git workflow for Projects.

Intern, (CENSE, Indian Institute of Science)

Bengaluru, India 09/2022 - 03/2024

- Development of LoRa (Long Range) based sensor network and LoRaWAN network infrastructure for tank level monitoring.
- Design and development of a custom Ultrasonic sensor for specific high humidity scenarios.

Skills

- **Programming:** C/C++ (Advanced), Python (Intermediate), PLC Programming (IEC 61131)
- Embedded Platforms: Linux, FreeRTOS, ZephyrOS
- Software Platforms: Docker, LabVIEW, Robotic Operating System (ROS), MATLAB/Simulink
- Management: Git, Jira, Confluence

Master's Thesis

TU Dortmund, Germany, 2024

- Title: Design and Development of a Novel Trust Framework for Humanoid Trust Behaviour in Multi-Robot Systems.
- Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Selma Saidi, Chair of Embedded Systems, TU Dortmund.
- Developed a mathematical model to quantify the trustworthiness of each robot in a Multi-Robot System (MRS) based on its inherent features, such as capabilities.
- Designed and developed a trust model that updates the robot's capabilities based on the outcomes of allocated tasks to the robots and evaluated the proposed novel trust framework against metrics such as trust convergence.
- Achieved 100% task allocation using the trust framework in a Python (using numpy, libraries) based simulation for a
 given mathematical distribution of incoming tasks to the MRS.
- Awarded Best Thesis with the highest possible grade of 1.0 (German grading system).

Race Against The Machine (RATM)

TU Dortmund, Germany, 2023

- Developed a racing scenario between a teleoperated vehicle and an autonomous vehicle.
- Established robust Teleoperated Driving over a 5G network.
- Implemented SLAM using Google Cartographer with Pure Pursuit control for autonomous navigation.
- Designed and Developed V2V and V2I communication using Cooperative Awareness Messages (CAM).
- Built a Digital Twin UI to show live vehicle positions on a map.

Bachelor's Thesis

RV College of Engineering, India, 2020

- Title: Design and Development of a PID based Control System for a Two Wheeled Self Balancing Robot.
- Developed a feedback control system for balancing a two wheeled robot vertically using NI LabVIEW and NI myRIO board.
- Designed a complementary filter for fusion of gyroscope and accelerometer data in order to achieve high accuracy tilt-angle measurement to be used as negative feedback.
- PID control algorithm tuned using Ziegler–Nichols method was used for controlling the duty cycle of PWM signal being given to the wheel motors to produce a balancing action.
- Implemented a sensor fusion model using a complementary filter combining gyroscope and accelerometer data.
- Awarded the highest achievable grade of 10.0 (Indian grading system).

Student Project

RV College of Engineering, India, 2019

- Signal processing of EEG signals to classify Alpha, Beta, Theta, and Delta (ABTD) waves.
- Correlation ABTD wave mapping with humanoid mood to control various music playlists.
- Developed APIs to control real-time devices using embedded systems.

Languages

• English [Native]

• **German** [Intermediate]

• Telugu, Kannada, Hindi [Native]